<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "SYSTEM" "jats-archiving-dtd-1.0/JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Bulletin of The Natural History Museum Zoology Series</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn>0968-0470</issn>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="biostor">113676</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0968047002000018</article-id>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Another variation on the gymnure theme: description of a new species of Hylomys (Lipotyphla, Erinaceidae, Galericinae)</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jenkins</surname>
            <given-names>Paulina D</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Robinson</surname>
            <given-names>Mark F</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <year>2002</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>68</volume>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>11</lpage>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <preformat></preformat>
    <preformat></preformat>
    <preformat>A NEW SPECIES OF HYLOMYS 

Fig. 1 Crania from left to right of dorsal view of mandible and skull, ventral view of skull, left lateral view of skull and mandible. Top row: Hylomys 
 megalotis BMNH 1999.47; second row: Hylomys suillus BMNH 1962.711: third row: Hylomys sinensis BMNH 1911.2.1.20; fourth row: Hylomys 
 parvus BMNH 1919.11.8.12. 

</preformat>
    <preformat>P.D. JENKINS AND M.F. ROBINSON 

Fig. 2 Lateral view of anterior of skull, mandible and dentition of Hylomys megalotis BMNH 1999.44. Scale = 1 mm. 

Comparison with other taxa 

The new species is readily distinguished in external appearance 
 from all other species of Hylomys. It is similar in body size but with 
 a considerably longer tail and larger ears (see Table 3). Tail 65-74 
 % of head and body length in H. megalotis, 5 1-63 % in H. sinensis, 
 27-3 1 % in H. hainanensis, and very short (&lt; 25 %) in H. par\&gt;us 
 and H. suillus. The lack of flattened spinous hairs in the pelage 
 distinguishes H. megalotis from H. suillus and H. sinensis. The 
 rhinarium is more extensive posteriorly than in H. sinensis but more 
 elongate and narrower than in H. suillus. The claws and first and 
 fifth digits of the forefeet of//, sinensis, H. suillus and H. pan&gt;us are 
 not lengthened as in H. megalotis and the cheiridia are smaller than 
 in H. megalotis. The sole and tarsal region of the hindfoot are naked 
 in H. megalotis, differing from the haired soles found in H. sinensis 
 and H. suillus. The paired pre-anal glands are midway between the 
 cloaca and the anus in H. sinensis and close to the anus in H. suillus, 
 so differing from that of H. megalotis, in which the single opening 
 is positioned immediately posterior to the cloaca. 

The skull of H. megalotis is more elongate in appearance than 
 any of the other species of Hylomys; it is longer, with a longer, 
 narrower rostrum, longer upper toothrow and the braincase is 
 shallower relative to its breadth (see (see Fig. 1 and Table 3). The 
 posterodorsal region of the premaxilla is widely separated from the 
 anterodorsal region of the frontal by the maxilla in H. megalotis, 
 narrowly separated in H. hainanensis but in contact or nearly in 
 contact in H. sinensis, H. suillus and H. parvus (see Table 4). As in 
 H. sinensis, but unlike other species of Hylomys, the posteriormost 

portion of the nasals in the new species extend to the level of the 
 antorbital rim. Hylomys megalotis has a shallow antorbital fossa 
 unlike the moderately deep fossa of H. sinensis and H. parvus, and 
 the deep fossa in H. suillus. The zygoma of//, megalotis differs from 
 all other species of Hylomys: the maxilla is considerably narrower, 
 the nasolabialis fossa shallower and the jugal more extensive. As in 
 Podogymnura aureospinula and Echinosorex, a distinct posteroventral 
 process is present on the maxillary region of the zygoma of H. 
 megalotis, indistinct in H. parvus but absent in H. suillus, H. sinensis 
 and H. hainanensis. The supraorbital process of the frontal of //. 
 megalotis is poorly defined and blunt, the anterior process of the 
 parietal absent and the parietal is widely separated from the maxilla 
 by the frontal in the supraorbital region, as in Podogymnura and 
 Echinosorex; in H. par\&gt;us the supraorbital process of the frontal is 
 poorly defined and blunt but the anterior process of the parietal is 
 short but distinct, narrowly separated from the maxilla by the frontal; 
 in H. suillus, H. hainanensis and H. sinensis the anterior process of 
 the parietal is distinct, scarcely separated from the maxilla and 
 contributing to the well marked supraorbital process of the frontal. 
 The optic and suboptic foramina are well separated in H. megalotis 
 but lie close together in H. suillus, H. sinensis and H. parvus. An 
 anteroventral process of the alisphenoid is present in H. megalotis, 
 unlike all other Hylomys and Podogymnura. As in Podogymnura and 
 Echinosorex, the palatine foramina are small and positioned anterior 
 to the maxillary /palatine suture in H. megalotis and long grooves for 
 the palatine artery are present in the palate, whereas the elongated 
 palatine foramina in other species of Hylomys lie at the maxillary/ 

</preformat>
    <preformat></preformat>
    <preformat>P.D. JENKINS AND M.F. ROBINSON 

E. gymnura 

P. aureospinula 

P. truei 

H. sinensis 

H. suillus 

H. hainanensis 

H. parvus 

H. megalotis 

Erinaceinae 

E. gymnura 

P. aureospinula 

P. truei 

H. sinensis 

H. hainanensis 

H. suillus 

H. parvus 

H. megalotis 

Erinaceinae 

Fig. 4 Comparison of trees obtained for the Galericinae. (a) One of twenty most parsimonious trees, all showing the same configuration for the 
 Galericinae. Tree length 141 steps, with a Consistency Index of 0.72, a Retention Index of 0.93, and a Rescaled Consistency index of 0.66. The 
 branching pattern on the left shows the results from the analysis of this study, that on the right is partially redrawn from Frost et al. (1991: fig. 9), 
 restricted to show only the relationships within the Galericinae and is 1 28 steps in length with a Consistency Index of 0.76. (b) One of the remaining 
 twenty most parsimonious trees, showing the alternate arrangement for the Galericinae. 

[66.1] M3 hypocone (see Frost et al. 1991) or metastylar spur (see 
 Gould, 1995): (0) absent or weak; (1) present, well developed on 
 buccal side. CI 1.000. 

[69.1] Axis, posteroventral keel: (0) absent; (1) present. CI 1.000. 
 [71.1] Scapula, metacromium process: (0) deltoid, amorphous pro- 
 jection; (1) long, fusiform projection. CI 1.000. 
 [72.1] Sacral vertebrae, neural spines: (0) not fused into continuous 
 longitudinal plate; ( 1 ) fused into continuous longitudinal plate. CI 
 1.000. 

[73.1] Ischium, posterodorsal process (see Gould, 1995 for correc- 
 tion of error by Frost et al. 1991): (0) not greatly elongated; (1) 
 greatly elongated. CI 1 .000. 

[74.1] Tibia, lateral flange on antero-superior margin: (0) absent or 
 weakly present; (1) strongly developed. CI 1.000. 

Synapomorphy of Hylomys: 

[19.1] Cranio-orbital foramen in the frontal: (0) closely associated or 
 joined with the ethmoid foramen; (1) foramina widely separated. 
 The terminology for this character is confusing. Frost et al. (1991) 
 used the name ophthalmic foramen (which they attributed to Butler 
 (1948) although this name could not be found in this paper), but 
 Gould (1995: character 19) pointed out that this foramen had been 
 misidentified by Butler and is the anterior opening for the superior 
 ramus of the stapedial artery. Gould also referred to this foramen as 

</preformat>
    <preformat>A NEW SPECIES OF HYLOMYS 

3 (64 

14 (97) 

4 (73) 

7 .(97' 

6 (83) 

6 (77) 

E. gymnura 

P. aureospinula 

P. true! 

H. sinensis 

H. hainanensis 

H. suillus 

H. parvus 

H. megalotis 

Erinaceinae 

Fig. 5 Strict consensus of 40 most parsimonious trees. The branch lengths are shown above the branches followed by the bootstrap support values in 
 parentheses, representing the percentage of trees containing the specified clades. The Bremer support indices are given below the branches. 

the sphenofrontal foramen and McDowell ( 1958) as the sinus canal. 
 CI 1.000. 

Synapomorphy of Hylomys sinensis, H. hainanensis, H. 

SUILLUS AND H. PARVUS: 

[4.1] Size of palatal foramina: (0) small; (1) anterior foramina 
 elongated posteriorly; (2) anterior foramina elongated to include 
 middle palatine foramina. CI 1.000. 

Synapomorphies of Hylomys sinensis, H. hainanensis, H. 

suillus: 

[13.1] Supraorbital process of frontal on parietal/frontal suture: (0) 

absent or poorly defined; ( 1 ) sharp, well defined. CI 1 .000. 

[16.1] Anterior process of parietal: (0) absent or very weak; (1) 

extends anteriorly along the supraorbital rim to form the base of the 

supraorbital process. CI 1.000. 

[57. 1 ] p3: (0) two roots present, larger in size than p2; ( 1 ) one root 

present, nearly equal in size to p2; (2) absent. CI 1.000. 

The analysis found no autapomorphic characters to define H. 
 megalotis but the following apomorphies for this species are recorded 
 as follows: 

[1.1] Posteriormost extension of nasals: (0) anterior to the level of 
 the antorbital rim; ( 1 ) medial or posterior to the level of the antorbital 
 rim. CI 0.333. Homoplasious with H. sinensis but also with 
 Erinaceinae. 

[5.1] Location of the anterior palatine foramina: (0) at the maxilla/ 
 palatine suture; ( 1 ) anterior to the maxilla/palatine suture. CI 0.500. 
 Shown only in DELTRAN, homoplasious with Echinosorex and 
 Podogymnura. 

[17.1] Anterior process of alisphenoid: (0) absent; (1) present. CI 
 0.500. Homoplasious with Erinaceinae. This character, defined as a 
 narrow, fusiform anterior process of the orbital wing of the alisphe- 
 noid is, according to Frost et al. (1991), related to the location of the 
 sphenopalatine foramen and involved with shortening of the 
 orbitotemporal region. Gould (1995) commented that the relative 
 position of the suboptic foramen (her character 21 scored thus: (0) 
 anterior to the sphenorbital fissure; ( 1 ) present in the medial wall of 
 the sphenorbital fissure; (2) present in the medial wall of the 
 sphenorbital fissure but hidden within the fissure) seems to be 

related to the shortening of the skull in erinaceids. As the skull 
 shortens, the alisphenoid overlaps the orbitosphenoid, creating a 
 strong alisphenoid wing [character 17 of Frost et al. (1991) and 
 Gould ( 1995)1, the degree of overlap seems to be directly related to 
 the visibility of the suboptic foramen from lateral view and, as 
 pointed out by Butler (1948) the orbitosphenoid is reduced in size. 
 While the alisphenoid is more extensive in H. megalotis than in other 
 galericines, and the suboptic and sphenorbital foramina are partially 
 concealed in lateral view, the orbitotemporal region is not obviously 
 shortened. The anterior process in H. megalotis is fully ventral in 
 location and is actually or nearly in contact with a short posteroventral 
 process of the maxilla, thus contributing to the ventral floor of the 
 orbit, however the orbitosphenoid is not reduced in size. It is 
 possible that this character state in H. megalotis is not homologous 
 with that of the Erinaceinae and that it actually represents a separate 
 character transformation, alternatively it is scored incorrectly and 
 the plesiomorphous condition should be the presence of the anterior 
 process. 

[22. 1 ] Palatal shelf and spine: (0) well developed spine on posterior 
 palatal shelf; ( 1 ) spine absent or vestigial. CI 0.200. Shown only in 
 DELTRAN, homoplasious with Podogymnura, H. parvus, and 
 Atelerix. 

DISCUSSION 

The addition of two taxa to the analysis performed by Frost et al. 
 ( 1 99 1 ) provided broadly similar results in that the Galericinae divided 
 into two main groups: one comprising Echinosorex andPodogymnura, 
 the second including all five species of Hylomys. The results of the 
 current phylogenetic analysis lend support to the taxonomy proposed 
 by Frost etal. (1991) that the three species of Hylomys considered in 
 their analysis (H. suillus, H. sinensis and H. hainanensis) are correctly 
 attributed to a single genus rather than the three separate genera 
 (respectively Hylomys, Neotetracus and Neohylomys) maintained by 
 Corbet (1988). The additional species of Hylomys however, reduced 
 the degree of support for the genus and, on this particular morphologi- 
 cal data set, a considerable degree of homoplasy is evident within the 
 Hylomys clade. There was only one unique synapomorphy for the 

</preformat>
    <preformat></preformat>
    <preformat>A NEW SPECIES OF HYLOMYS 
 Table 1 Comparative material 

Hylomys 

BMNH I 
 BMNH 1 
 BMNH 1 
 BMNH 

China] 
 BMNH 1 

China] 
 MNHN 1 
 BMNH 
 BMNH 
 BMNH 
 BMNH 

932.4.19.3 Chapa. Tonkin, [Vietnam] 

933.4. 1.1 17-1 34 Chapa, Tonkin, [Vietnam] 

933.4.1.536-541 Chapa, Tonkin, [Vietnam] 

9 1 1 .2. 1 . 1 5-23 Omi-san, Omi-Hsien, S. Szechwan [Sichuan, PDR 

I 

982.205 Omi-san, Omi-Hsien, S. Szechwan [Sichuan, PDR 

I 

9 1 1 - 1 1 80- 1 1 84 Ta-Tsien-Lou, Setchouen [Sichuan, PDR China] 

909. 12.13.1 Ta-Tsien-Lou, Szechuan [Sichuan, PDR China] 

911.8.6.1 Yengyuek. Yunnan, [PDR China] 

912.7.15.1 Ching-tsai-Yang, Yunnan, [PDR China] 

914.10.23.3 Near Yang-fsi, W. Yunnan, [PDR China] 

Hylomys suillus 

BMNH 1909.7.20.2-3 Sima. Burma [Myanmar] 

AMNH 441 1 2 Nam-Ting, Yunnan, China [PDR China] 

BMNH 1925. 1 . 1 . 1 7 Bao-Ha, Tonkin, [Vietnam] 

BMNH 1926.10.4.42 Xieng-Khouang, Laos [Lao PDR] 

AMNH 87313 Bologens Plateau, Laos [Lao PDR] 

BMNH 1926.10.4.36-41 Dak-to, Annam 

MNHN 1929-320-325 Dak-to, Annam 

BMNH 1955.1422 Tasan,Chumpawn, Peninsular Siam [Thailand] 

TISTR 54-61 1 Huey Mae Sanam, Chiengmai, Thailand 

TISTR 54-613 Trang, Muang, Chong. Thailand 

TISTR 54-614-615 Khao Yai National Park, Korat, Thailand 

TISTR 54-616 Phu Nam Tok, Saraburi, Thailand 

TISTR 54-617 Pok Nam Tok, 21 km from Saraburi, Saraburi, Thailand 

TISTR 54-618 Mae Sai, B. Santon Poi, Chieng Rai, Thailand 

TISTR 54-1498-1500 Pak Thong Chai, Sakaerat, Nakhon Ratchasima. 

Thailand 
 TISTR 54- 1 8 1 1 Pak Thong Chai, 1 7 km S of Pak Thong Chai, Nakhon 

Ratchasima. Thailand 
 TISTR 54-1809-1810 Khon San, Pa Phu Khieo, Chaiyaphum, Thailand 
 TISTR 54-1812 Phu Kradung National Park, Loei, Thailand 
 BMNH 1960.8.4.7 Ulu Langat Forest Reserve, Kajang, Selangor, 

[Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1961.1158 Ulu Langat Forest Reserve. Kajang. Selangor, 

Malaysia 
 BMNH 1955.1420 Semangko Pass, Pahang, Federal Malay States 

[Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1961.1 159 Padang, Jeriau, Fraser's Hill, Pahang, Malaysia 
 BMNH 1962.710-711 Jandai Baik, Pahang, Malaysia 
 BMNH 1912.10.22.7 Pelarit, Perlis, Malay [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1955.1421 Pelarit, Perlis, Federal Malay States [Malaysia] 

BMNH 1912.10.22.8 Perlis, Malay Peninsula [Malaysia] 

BMNH 1955.1423 Jor, Batang Pasang, Perak, Federal Malay States 

[Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1955.1424 Kedah Peak, Federal Malay States [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1962.71 la Kedah Peak. Kedah, Malaya [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1892.9.6.4 Mt. Kina Balu [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1895.10.4.3^ Mt. Kina Balu [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1955.661 Mount Kinabalu. British North Borneo [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1971.2614-2615 Mt. Kinabalu, N Borneo [Malaysia] 
 MNHN 1889-37 Mont Kina Balu. Borneo [Malaysia] 
 MNHN 1893-132-133 Mont Kina Balu, Borneo [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1971.2616 Dusan Dankulum, Kinabalu, N Borneo [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1971.2617-2618 Tinampoh, Bundu Tuhan rest house, N Borneo 

[Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1919.1 1.5.7 Korinchi, Sumatra [Sumatera, Indonesia] 
 AMNH 102532 Seletan. Mocamh Doewa, Sumatra [Sumatera, Indonesia] 
 AMNH 102533 Seletan. Mocamh Doewa. Sumatra [Sumatera, Indonesia] 
 AMNH 102534 Seletan, Mocamh Doewa. Sumatra [Sumatera. Indonesia] 
 AMNH 102820 Lampung. Kalianda. Sumatra [Sumatera. Indonesia] 
 BMNH 1954.45 Tjibodas. West Java [Jawa. Indonesia] 
 BMNH 1954.46-48 Sodong Jerok. Idjen Massif. East Java [Jawa. 

Indonesia] 
 BMNH 1961.1743 Tjemorosewu. Mt. Lawu. Java [Jawa. Indonesia] 
 AMNH 106111 Java [Jawa. Indonesia] 

Hylomys parvus 

BMNH 1919.1 1.5.8-12 Korinchi, Sumatra [Sumatera, Indonesia] 

Podogymnura truei 

BMNH 1953.659-660 Baclayan. E slopes of Mount Apo, Mindanao, 
 Philippine Islands 

Echinosorex gymmiru 

BMNH 1914.12.8.101-104 Bankachon, Tenasserim [Myanmar] 

BMNH 1955.1452 Changkat Mentri. Perak, Federal Malay States 

[Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1955.1453 Damansara Road. Kuala Lumpur, Selangor, Federal 

Malay States [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1961.1 156 Rontau Panjang. Klang. Selangor, Malaya [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1961.1 157 Sungei Buloh, Selangor. Malaya [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1 96 1.1157 Sungei Buloh. Selangor. Malaya [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1951.179-180 Mount Dulit, Sarawak. Borneo [Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1951.181 Tinjar River, Baram District. Sarawak, Borneo 

[Malaysia] 
 BMNH 1 97 1 .26 1 3 1 2 miles N of Kalabakan. Tawau. N Borneo [Malaysia] 

</preformat>
    <preformat></preformat>
    <preformat></preformat>
    <supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages">
      <graphic xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pagethumb/41008501" xlink:role="41008501" xlink:title="scanned-page"/>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pagethumb/41008500" xlink:role="41008500" xlink:title="scanned-page"/>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pagethumb/41008499" xlink:role="41008499" xlink:title="scanned-page"/>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pagethumb/41008498" xlink:role="41008498" xlink:title="scanned-page"/>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pagethumb/41008497" xlink:role="41008497" xlink:title="scanned-page"/>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pagethumb/41008496" xlink:role="41008496" xlink:title="scanned-page"/>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pagethumb/41008495" xlink:role="41008495" xlink:title="scanned-page"/>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pagethumb/41008494" xlink:role="41008494" xlink:title="scanned-page"/>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pagethumb/41008493" xlink:role="41008493" xlink:title="scanned-page"/>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pagethumb/41008492" xlink:role="41008492" xlink:title="scanned-page"/>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pagethumb/41008491" xlink:role="41008491" xlink:title="scanned-page"/>
    </supplementary-material>
  </body>
</article>
