
<!DOCTYPE tp:taxon-treatment
  PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NSO.dtd">
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub"><tp:treatment-meta><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sulca</surname><given-names>Lidia</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharkey</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three new species of <italic>Sesioctonus</italic> Viereck (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Agathidinae) from Peru</article-title><source>Zookeys</source><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><issue>196</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.196.3086</pub-id></mixed-citation></tp:treatment-meta><tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Sesioctonus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">wayquecha</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:19BD24A0-162D-405A-8BF0-5CDA62C5FE86</object-id>
								<object-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Sesioctonus_wayquecha</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-authority>Sulca &amp; Sharkey</tp:taxon-authority><tp:taxon-status xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2 a,b,c,d</xref></tp:nomenclature><tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title><p>Distinguished from all other known species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sesioctonus</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the following suite of characters: occipital tubercles absent, epicnemial carina completely absent, antennal socket not excavated, gena moderately expanded posteroventrally .</p></tp:treatment-sec><tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title><p>♀ <italic>Length</italic>. Length of body, excluding ovipositor, 4.3–5.5 mm.</p><p><italic>Head</italic>. Flagellum with 31 flagellomeres. Interantennal space lacking longitudinal keel. Antennal sockets not excavated. Face without median longitudinal carina. Gena moderately expanded posteroventrally. Occipital tubercles absent. Occiput not excavated. Mandible concave. Outer tooth of mandible not longer than inner tooth. Maxillary palpus with 5 palpomeres. Third and fourth labial palpomeres not fused. <italic>Mesosoma</italic>. Subpronope elongate-oval. Longitudinal carinae of scutellar depression absent. Scutellum convex. Median areola of metanotum smooth, without median longitudinal carina, and with lateral carinae present and meeting posteriorly. Propodeum convex. Median longitudinal carina of propodeum absent. Epicnemial carina completely absent. Fore tibial spines present. Mid tibia with 7 spines. Hind tibia with 15 spines. Hind femur 3.3–4 times as long as wide. (RS+M)a vein of fore wing complete. 3RSa<!--PageBreak--> vein of fore wing absent. 2–1A vein of hind wing not tubular. Cub vein of hind wing not tubular. <italic>Metasoma</italic>. Median tergite of first metasomal segment without pair of lateral longitudinal carinae. Hind wing with 4 hamuli. First metasomal median tergite without depression posteriad spiracle. Length/width ratio of first metasomal median tergite 0.63. Ovipositor 0.5–0.6 mm.</p><p><italic>Color</italic>. Head melanic. Antenna melanic. Maxillary palpomeres yellowish orange. Labial palpomeres yellowish orange. Pronotum melanic. Mesoscutum melanic. Scutellum melanic. Metanotum melanic. Propodeum mostly yellowish orange with melanic spots. Propleuron mostly melanic with yellowish orange areas. Mesopleuron melanic. Metapleuron yellowish orange. Fore coxa yellowish orange. Fore trochanter yellowish orange. Fore trochantellus yellowish orange. Fore femur yellowish orange. Fore tibia melanic with yellowish orange ends. Fore tarsus melanic. Mid coxa yellowish orange. Mid trochanter yellowish orange. Mid trochantellus yellowish orange. Mid femur yellowish orange. Mid tibia melanic. Mid tarsus melanic. Hind coxa yellowish orange. Hind trochanter yellowish orange. Hind trochantellus yellowish orange. Hind femur yellowish orange. Hind tibia melanic with a yellow orange apical spot. Hind tarsus melanic. Fore wing entirely infuscate. Stigma melanic. Hind wing entirely infuscate. First metasomal tergum yellowish orange. Second metasomal tergum yellowish orange. Third metasomal tergum yellowish orange. Fourth metasomal tergum yellowish orange but median tergum melanic. Fifth to eighth metasomal terga melanic. Ovipositor yellowish orange.</p><p>♂. As in the female (above).</p><p><!--PageBreak--><italic>Etymology</italic>. Named after the type locality, Wayquecha which means ‘brother’ in Quechua.</p><p><italic>Holotype</italic>. PERU. ♀,Cusco, Wayquecha, <named-content xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">13°11'21"S, 71°35'04"W</named-content> 2837m ,6– 20.x.2007, C. Castillo. Leg.</p><p><italic>Paratypes</italic>: PERU: Cusco: 2♀♀,Wayquecha, <named-content xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">13°11'21"S, 71°35'4"W</named-content>, 2837m, Malaise, 20.x.2007, C. Castillo Leg.; 3♀♀, 1♂,Wayquecha, <named-content xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">13°10'31"S, 71°34'53"W</named-content>, 2692m, Malaise, 10.ix.2007, C. Castillo Leg.; ♀, Wayquecha <named-content xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">13°11'S, 71°35'W</named-content>, 2800m, sweep, 12.ix.2007, C. Castillo Leg; ♂ Wayquecha, <named-content xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">13°10'31"S, 71°34'53"W</named-content>, 2692m, Malaise, 22.x.2007, C. Castillo Leg.</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sesioctonus wayquecha</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <bold>2a</bold> lateral habitus <bold>2b</bold> wings <bold>2c</bold> dorsal scutellum and propodeum  <bold>2d</bold> anterior head <bold>2e</bold> dorsal habitus.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ZooKeys-196-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></tp:treatment-sec><tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title><p>Known only from one locality in Peru.</p></tp:treatment-sec></tp:taxon-treatment>