
<!DOCTYPE tp:taxon-treatment
  PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NSO.dtd">
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub"><tp:treatment-meta><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sulca</surname><given-names>Lidia</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharkey</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three new species of <italic>Sesioctonus</italic> Viereck (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Agathidinae) from Peru</article-title><source>Zookeys</source><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><issue>196</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.196.3086</pub-id></mixed-citation></tp:treatment-meta><tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Sesioctonus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">huggerti</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A198E0BC-7DFE-42CB-B5AD-9DF7E63597E6</object-id>
								<object-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Sesioctonus_huggerti</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-authority>Sulca &amp; Sharkey</tp:taxon-authority><tp:taxon-status xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref></tp:nomenclature><tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title><p>Distinguished from all other known species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sesioctonus</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the following suite of characters: Interantennal space lacking longitudinal keel, epicnemial carinae straight medially.</p></tp:treatment-sec><tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title><p>♀ <italic>Length</italic>. Length of body, excluding ovipositor, 5 mm.</p><p><italic>Head</italic>. Flagellum with 30 flagellomeres. Interantennal space lacking longitudinal keel. Antennal sockets moderately excavated. Face with median longitudinal carina. Gena not expanded posteroventrally. Occipital tubercles present. Occiput not excavated. Mandible concave. Outer tooth of mandible not longer than inner tooth. Maxillary palpus with 4 palpomeres. Third and fourth labial palpomeres not fused. <italic>Mesosoma</italic>. Subpronope elongate-oval. Longitudinal carinae of scutellar depression absent. Scutellum convex. Median areola of metanotum smooth, with median longitudinal carina, and with lateral carinae present and not meeting posteriorly. Propodeum convex. Median longitudinal carina of propodeum absent. Epicnemial carina complete, sharp, straight medially (between fore coxae). Hind femur 6 times as long as wide. (RS+M)a vein of fore wing incomplete. 3RSa vein of fore wing absent. 2–1A vein of hind wing not tubular. Cub vein of hind wing not tubular. <italic>Metasoma</italic>. Median tergite of first metasomal segment without pair of lateral longitudinal carinae. Hind wing with 4 hamuli. First metasomal median tergite without depression posteriad spiracle. Length/width ratio of first metasomal median tergite 0.63. Ovipositor 4 mm.</p><p><italic>Color</italic>. Head melanic. Maxillary palpomeres melanic. Labial palpomeres melanic. Pronotum melanic. Mesoscutum yellowish orange. Scutellum yellowish orange. Metanotum yellowish orange. Propodeum melanic. Propleuron melanic. Mesopleuron yellowish orange. Metapleuron melanic. Fore coxa melanic. Fore trochanter melanic. Fore trochantellus melanic. Fore femur melanic. Fore tibia melanic. Fore tarsus melanic. Mid coxa melanic. Mid trochanter melanic. Mid trochantellus melanic. Midfemur melanic. Mid tibia melanic. Mid tarsus melanic. Hind coxa melanic. Hind trochanter melanic. Hind trochantellus melanic. Hind femur melanic. Hind tibia melanic. Hind tarsus melanic. Fore wing entirely infuscate. Stigma melanic. Hind wing entirely infuscate. First metasomal tergum melanic. Second metasomal tergum me<!--PageBreak-->lanic. Third metasomal tergum melanic. Fourth metasomal tergum melanic. Fifth to eighth metasomal terga melanic. Ovipositor yellowish orange.</p><p>♂ Unknown.</p><p><italic>Etymology</italic>. Named in honor of the late Lars Huggert who collected the type specimen.</p><p><italic>Holotype</italic>. PERU, Madre de Dios, Puerto Maldonado, 6–11.i.1984, L. Huggert Leg. (Canadian National Collection).</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sesioctonus huggerti</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <bold>1a</bold> dorsal habitus <bold>1b</bold> lateral habitus <bold>1c</bold> wings <bold>1d</bold> propodeum and first metasomal segment.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ZooKeys-196-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></tp:treatment-sec><tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title><p>Known only from the type locality in Peru.</p></tp:treatment-sec></tp:taxon-treatment>