
<!DOCTYPE tp:taxon-treatment
  PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NSO.dtd">
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub"><tp:treatment-meta><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sulca</surname><given-names>Lidia</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharkey</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three new species of <italic>Sesioctonus</italic> Viereck (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Agathidinae) from Peru</article-title><source>Zookeys</source><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><issue>196</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.196.3086</pub-id></mixed-citation></tp:treatment-meta><tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Sesioctonus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">bina</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5AE5EEED-ACF8-47D4-8189-531FFDBB1209</object-id>
								<object-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Sesioctonus_bina</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-authority>Sulca &amp; Sharkey</tp:taxon-authority><tp:taxon-status xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref></tp:nomenclature><tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title><p>Distinguished from all other known species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sesioctonus</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the following suite of characters: occiput not excavated, subpronope oval, median tergite of first metasomal segment with pair of lateral longitudinal carinae.</p></tp:treatment-sec><tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title><p>♀ <italic>Length</italic>. Length of body, excluding ovipositor, 3.35 mm. Flagellum broken after flagellomere 28. Interantennal space with longitudinal rounded keel. Antennal sockets moderately excavated. Face without median longitudinal carina. Gena not expanded posteroventrally. Occipital tubercles present. Occiput not excavated. Mandible concave. Outer tooth of mandible not longer than inner tooth. Maxillary palpus with 4 palpomeres. <italic>Mesosoma</italic>. Subpronope oval. Longitudinal carinae of scutellar depression absent. Scutellum convex. Median areola of metanotum smooth, without median longitudinal carina, and with lateral carinae present and meeting posteriorly. Propodeum convex. Median longitudinal carina of propodeum present. Epicnemial carina complete, blunt, bilobed medially (between fore coxae). Fore tibial spines present. Mid tibia with 3 spines. Hind tibia with 12 spines. Hind femur 4 times as long as wide. (RS+M)a vein of fore wing incomplete. 3RSa vein of fore wing present. 2–1A vein of hind wing tubular. Cub vein of hind wing not tubular. <italic>Metasoma</italic>. Median tergite of first metasomal segment with pair of lateral longitudinal carinae. Hind wing with 3 hamuli. First metasomal median tergite without depression posteriad spiracle. Length width ratio of first metasomal median tergite 0.5. Ovipositor 1.68 mm.</p><p><italic>Color</italic>. Head black and yellowish orange. Antenna melanic. Maxillary palpomeres yellowish orange. Labial palpomeres yellowish orange. Pronotum melanic. Mesoscutum melanic. Scutellum melanic. Metanotum melanic. Propodeum melanic. Propleuron melanic. Mesopleuron melanic. Metapleuron melanic. Fore coxa yellowish orange. Fore trochanter yellowish orange. Fore trochantellus yellowish orange. Fore femur yellowish orange. Fore tibia yellowish orange. Fore tarsus mostly yellowish orange, but apical tarsomere melanic. Mid coxa yellowish orange. Mid trochanter yellowish orange. Mid<!--PageBreak--> trochantellus yellowish orange. Mid femur yellowish orange. Mid tibia yellowish orange in basal half, melanic apically, or yellowish orange basally, otherwise melanic. Mid tarsus melanic. Hind coxa melanic. Hind trochanter melanic. Hind trochantellus melanic. Hind femur melanic. Hind tibia melanic in basal and apical third, yellowish orange medially. Hind tarsus melanic. Fore wing entirely infuscate. Stigma melanic. Hind wing entirely infuscate. First metasomal tergum melanic. Second metasomal tergum yellowish orange but median tergite melanic. Third metasomal tergum melanic. Fourth metasomal tergum melanic. Fifth to eighth metasomal terga melanic. Ovipositor yellowish orange.</p><p>♂ unknown</p><p><italic>Etymology</italic>. Bina means ‘wasp’ in Shipibo, an indigenous language of the Peruvian Amazon.</p><p><italic>Holotype</italic>. ♀, PERU, Cusco, Rocotal, 16.ix.2007, Sweep, C. Castillo Leg.</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sesioctonus bina</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <bold>3a</bold> lateral head and mesosoma <bold>3b</bold> lateral habitus <bold>3c</bold> wings <bold>3d</bold> propodeum and first metasomal segment.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ZooKeys-196-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></tp:treatment-sec></tp:taxon-treatment>